So welcome to our lecture where we start talking
about the speed clock speed how circuits have
delay. In the previous lecture we introduced for
the first time the notion of a clock and that is
a value that is at zero and then when we want
something to happen we set it to one and when
we're done we set it back to zero. Now this is
a circuit. It's a combinatoric circuit. And if
you play with this online, you'll see that it you
change a number and it takes a little bit of time
for the propagation to end up at the out output of
this circuit. And that's just because it's kind of
slow in my online emulator. This is a full ladder
circuit and this is not a very long circuit,
but you can see over time how these are going
to get longer, especially when we start chaining
them. Right? So if we make a four-bit adder,
that's four full adders where the carry out
goes to the carry-in, the carry out of the second
one goes to the carry-in of the third, and the
carry out of the third one goes to the fourth.
Now, those values will only settle down after
the carries have propagated all the way down that
chain. And that's just a 4-bit adder. You could
have a 32-bit adder or a 64-bit adder or even a
multiplier in hardware. And so the the propagation
through a 64-bit multiplier is going to take
a little while. And so these circuits get more
complex than what we've done. But when they build
them, they'll make a 64-bit adder. It takes two
operands and produces a result. And the designers
of the chip hardware will simulate and simulate
and tweak it and simulate and simulate it. Um,
how long is it that if you present inputs to a
64-bit adder until the outputs are reliable and
no longer changing? Okay. And that's called the
clock rate. And and if we take a a microprocessor,
we compute the delay of the slowest element or
longest path in the arithmetic and logic unit. We
can determine the number of times to per second
we can reliably do computations. And then we
set the clock rate to be a little conservative.
Okay. And so this is a another example of the
Intel 4004, which is our favorite little first
widely available commercial microprocessor.
And so as microprocessors have gotten smaller,
as the width of each wire and the width of
transistors have gotten smaller, you can make
the distances between the transistors smaller. as
we went to seaoss and we could manage heat better,
we could put things more tightly packed, the more
tightly packed we do, the faster they go. And so,
um, this is a graph of a thing called Moore's
law. And it was something that people just started
seeing once we would improve the technology,
then we would build microprocessors with that
new technology. Then we improve the architecture
of those microprocessors and then we would do
new technology. It turned out that the number of
integrated circuits and pretty much for a while
the clock speed of them would double about every
eight every two years. So how do we know what the
clock rate is? Like I mentioned the size of the
chip because when we're doing things this fast the
speed of light matters the number of transistors
because each transistor takes a little while to
flip as you change its input and its output
needs to change. the physical length of thing
of any long path. And just because a chip is uh
one inch wide doesn't mean there's not paths that
are several inches because they go around and go
back and forth and the speed at which transistors
switch. And this depends on the technology
and it gets better over time. And like I said,
these chips are laid out and simulated endlessly
during development to figure out how we can take
this chip. And then you've probably heard about
people overclocking their chips and that's when
someone changes the clock because they think that
the factory was being too conservative on the
clock rate. So let's add 10% and see if it starts
blowing up. And that's called overclocking. So
let's play with a simple circuit. We're going to
take two of the circuits that we built in previous
lectures and combine them together. So what we're
going to do is we're going to take an adder and a
clock and a register. So the adder simply takes
two three-bit numbers from 0 through 7 on the A,
ones, twos, and fours for the A and ones,
twos, and fours for the B. And so we have our
two operands. We have our sum values which are the
sum and they are copied to the input values of our
latch. and we have a clock on the latch because if
you recall while the clock is low, we don't care
about the input changes. Okay, so right now our
adder is zero. We are adding 0 plus 0 and getting
zero. Our latch is still a zero, not because the
adder is zero, but because the clock is zero and
the latch was zero before. If we change the input
on the adder, we are going to do a 2 + 4. A is 2,
B is four. and the adder now has produced it.
There's a delay there, but you'll notice the
latch hasn't changed because we haven't pressed
the clock yet. The clock is still at zero. And
the definition of the clock in a latch is that the
latch is ignoring its input change. Any changes
on input until the clock goes one. So when the
clock goes one, the sum values are latched into
the latch memory. Now, if you keep the clock
one and fiddle with the inputs of the adder,
then you're not sure what's happening because it
may take a while to go through the adder or it
might come through very quickly. But the smart
thing to do is then set the clock back to zero
because we have the sum copied from the adder.
And now we can change the inputs. Right? Once we
have the clock at zero, we can just feed different
inputs into the adder. So now we're adding 4 plus
3. Now the clock is still zero and we have changed
the inputs to the adder. We're now adding 4 + 3
with the adder is reflecting the sum as soon as
we change those inputs. Right? The adder just as
a combinatoric circuit takes its inputs produces
the output. But because the clock is still zero,
the clock is low, the latch hasn't accepted those
values yet. Right? When the clock goes high,
the seven is going to be copied into the new
latch value. Now, if we do this, you can build
this circuit with my little circuit emulator. You
can build the circuit where you have the adder,
you have a latch, and you can interactively play
with the ones, twos, and fours for both the A
input and the B input. But instead of having
a button for the clock, we have a programmable
clock. And the clock object goes from 0ero to
one back to zero every second. So what happens
is you can fiddle with the inputs of this. See
how fast you can change them. And every second
whatever is in the adder is going to be copied
into the latch. Now we're going to go a little
farther in the next lecture with what we're doing
with clocks and gates and adders and latches.